Native Americans RHS-Coll-0062
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Native Americans
1872-1988
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
The Roanoke Times
Lexington Gazette. (Lexington, Va.)
RHS-Coll-0062
10 Files Folders 1-10, RHS-Coll #0060-0076
RHS Collections #0060 - #0076
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of files containing newspaper articles, history essays and writing, and photographs concerning Native American land, battles with colonial settlers, prominent figures, and forts in Rockbridge County. Many materials describe the Shawnee Tribe and their presence and relationship with settlers in Kerrs Creek, Abbs' Valley, Balcony Falls, and Hayes Creek Mound. Some materials concern the death of Chief Cornstalk, also known as Hokoleskwa, and the Kerrs Creek Massacre.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open to research use.
Shawnee Indians; Virginia -- Rockbridge County; Battles; Rockbridge County, Virginia; Chief Cornstalk
- General, 20th century newspaper articles describing events in the 1750s.; The Roanoke Times; Lexington Gazette. (Lexington, Va.) (RHS Collections #0060 - #0076, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  This file contains a Lexington Gazette article describing a general history of Native American presence and conflict in Rockbridge County, an article on a Shawnee raid on cabins located on Purgatory Creek, and a manuscript chapter recounting a settler's child being kidnapped by Native Americans.
  Shawnee Indians -- Wars
- Abbs Valley, 1935-12-26; Lexington Gazette. (Lexington, Va.) (RHS Collections #0060 - #0076, Folder 2)
  Contains a newspaper article documenting the story of Abbs Valley, and the conflict between Native Americans and the Moore family in mid-18th century.
  Moore, James Julius; Moore Family
- Balcony Falls (RHS Collections #0060 - #0076, Folder 3)
  Contains semi-dramatized account of violent interaction between numerous then-Augusta county citizens and a local Native American tribe near Balcony Falls, resulting in numerous deaths on both sides.
  Shawnee Indians; Greenlee family; McDowell, John, 1706-1742; Moore, James
- Battle of 1742, 1906-04 (RHS Collections #0060 - #0076, Folder 4)
  Contains 1906 report on the Battle of 1942, which involved a number of notable Rockbridge County citizens in a violent conflict with Native American tribes.
  Rockbridge County (Va.) -- Land settlement; Catawba Indians; Iroquois Indians; Patton, James; McDowell, John, 1706-1742; McDowell, Ephriam, 1672-1775; McDowell, Samuel, 1735-1817; James River
- Cornstalk, 1926-10-28; 1935-02 (RHS Collections #0060 - #0076, Folder 5)
  This file consists of three articles written on Chief Cornstalk, and his involvement in violent raids that occured in Rockbridge County, as well as his death at the hands of a soldier, Jacob Hull, in 1777 in Point Pleasant. Cornstalk led battles during Pontiac's Raid.
  Shawnee Indians; Rockbridge County (Va.) -- Land settlement; Chief Cornstalk; Lewis, Andrew
- Forts, 1960-02; The Roanoke Times (RHS Collections #0060 - #0076, Folder 6)
  This file constains a group of serially published newspaper articles on the history of George Washington developing and using frontier forts in order to create defensive structures to limit casualties and damages from Native American raids and conflicts. Articles published between February 14th to March 6th, 1960.
  Rockbridge County (Va.) -- Land settlement; Shawnee Indians; Washington, George
- Hayes Creek Mound, 1901-09; Valentine, Edward Pleasants (RHS Collections #0060 - #0076, Folder 7)
  This file contains two copies of the "Report of the Exploration of the Hayes Creek Mound Rockbridge County, Va." The report includes a typewritten note from F.P. Tompkins noting that this particular edition was gifted to the librarian of the Rockbridge Historical Society. The report includes a brief description of the state of the burial grouds and the positions the bodies were laid in upon excavation. The report also includes a drawn diagram of the burial site, as well as plates of photographs depicting skeletons. Written by Edward P. Valentine, for the Valentine Museum in Richmond, VA.
  Burial; Mounds; Rockbridge County (Va.) -- Land settlement
- Kerrs Creek, 1872-01-1988-04-15 (RHS Collections #0060 - #0076, Folder 8)
  This file consists of a handwritten account by Harvey Hotinger, reproduced and photocopied versions of articles related to the Kerrs Creek Massacre and other Native American and settler conflict in the area. Includes a copy of an interview with Jane Gay Stevenson sent from Charles Estell Baker of Center Point Independent Church of Birmingham Alabama. Also contains a report written by Madeline Gillespie entitled "Kerr's Creek Indian Raids" from 1955.
  Shawnee Indians; Rockbridge County (Va.) -- Land settlement; Moore, John Lyle
- Paul's Fort, 1970-05-03; The Roanoke Times (RHS Collections #0060 - #0076, Folder 9)
  This file consists of a copy of a Roanoke Times article entitled "Highway Passes Over Site of Fort" by George Wilson. Talks about viewing the fort from their perspective in the 1970s.
  Rockbridge County (Va.) -- Land settlement; Shawnee Indians; Diehl, George West; Big Spring Mill; Patton, James; Preston, William; Lewis, Andrew
- Walnut Fort, 1936-05-15; Lexington Gazette. (Lexington, Va.) (RHS Collections #0060 - #0076, Folder 10)
  This file consists of a handwritten manuscript draft entitled "Walnut Fort," later published in the Lexington Gazette on May 15th, 1936. The document describes the physical features of the fort, the cooking practices of those who lived there, other domestic qualities, and the familial history of those who inhabited and maintained the fort.
  Virginia -- Rockbridge County; Walker family; Staurt, Archibald Paxton; Borden, Benjamin, Sr.; Stuart, John Leighton; Lewis, William Cook